Guide to the Robert Leslie Papers, 1783-1934 and undated, bulk 1814-1872 RL.00806
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Robert Leslie papers
1783-1934 and undated, bulk 1814-1872
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Leslie, Robert, ca. 1794-ca. 1879
RL.00806
23.7 Linear Feet
Merchant, of Petersburg, Va. Correspondence, accounts, invoices, statements, and legal papers (chiefly 1814-1872) of Leslie, a member of the Virginia mercantile firm of Leslie and Shepherd, and a slave owner. The papers before 1819 largely concern the processing and sale of cotton, tobacco, rice, and western lands. Most of the papers after 1819 pertain to tobacco manufacture in the Richmond-Petersburg area. Other topics include Leslie's career, family, and travels in England; his western landholdings and efforts to develop the West; his slaveholding and attitude toward it; mercantile prices and U.S.-British trade; and absentee landlordship referring to the maintenance of American property owned by Englishmen. Later material includes scattered correspondence and business papers of Leslie's nephews, Robert L. Watson and John McGill, whom Leslie had admitted to partnership in the firm.
Approximately 15,398 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Robert Leslie papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1950.
Collection Overview
Correspondence, accounts, invoices, statements, and legal papers, chiefly spanning the years 1814-1872, of Robert Leslie, a member of the Virginia mercantile firm of Leslie and Shepherd, and a slave owner. The papers before 1819 largely concern the processing and sale of cotton, tobacco, rice, and western lands. Most of the papers after 1819 pertain to tobacco manufacture in the Richmond-Petersburg area. Other topics include Leslie's career, family, and travels in England; his western landholdings and efforts to develop the West; his slaveholding and attitude toward it; mercantile prices and U.S.-British trade; and absentee landlordship referring to the maintenance of American property owned by Englishmen. Later material includes scattered correspondence and business papers of Leslie's nephews, Robert L. Watson and John McGill, whom Leslie had admitted to partnership in the firm.
Commission merchants -- Virginia -- Petersburg; Absentee landlordism; England -- Description and travel; Cotton trade -- Virginia; Land settlement -- West (U.S.); Great Britain -- Commerce -- United States; Rice trade -- Virginia; Merchants -- Virginia -- Petersburg; Tobacco -- Marketing -- Virginia; United States -- Commerce -- Great Britain; Slaveholders -- Virginia; Slavery -- Virginia; Virginia -- Economic conditions; Leslie and Shepherd (Petersburg, Va.); McGill, J. F. (John F.); Watson, Robert L.
- Correspondence Series, 1783-1934, bulk 1814-1872, 35 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1783-1827 Jan-Sept. (Box 1)
  - 1823-1852 (oversize) (Box 9)
  - 1827 Oct.-Dec.-1830 Oct. (Box 2)
  - 1830 Nov.-Dec.-1834 Apr. (Box 3)
  - 1834 May-1836 Feb.-Jun. (Box 4)
  - 1836 Jul-1840 Jun. (Box 5)
  - 1840 Jul.-1849 Apr. (Box 6)
  - 1849 May-1858 (Box 7)
  - 1853-1899 (oversize) (Box 10)
  - 1859-1934 (Box 8)
- Financial Papers Series, 1820s-1899 and undated, 12 boxes
  - Bills and receipts
    - 1820s-1830s (Box 11)
    - 1830s (Box 12)
    - 1830s-1850s (Box 13)
    - 1850s-1860s (Box 14)
    - Undated papers (Box 14-15)
    - Undated papers (oversize), 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Volumes, cashbooks, 1850-1899 (Box 15)